<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE note SYSTEM "divination_xml.dtd">
<document>
<document_name>DIVINATION IN THAILAND: The hopes and fears of a Southeast Asian people, Portentous Pimples</document_name>
(Curzon Press, 1983)
H. G. QUARITCH WALES
Chapter 3, pp 47–50

Another form of divination which lends itself, though again not exclusively, to discovering the immediate outlook is provided by the consideration of pimples.
By their very nature many types of pimples can appear suddenly, at any age, thereby suggesting that they convey a revelation as to the near future.
I should not like to be dogmatic as to the proximate direction from which this form of divination reached the Thai, but I think that an ultimately Indian origin is likely.
It is certainly attested for the Buddhist kingdom over which ruled King Milinda.
In answer to a question from the king, the monk Nagasena replied ‘According to the places on which the pimples have arisen, the fortune-tellers, making their observations, give decision, saying “Such and such will be the result”.
Again Varāhamihira, the famous sixth century A.D. Indian astronomer cum astrologer (though the chapter is suspected of being a later interpolation), gives a list of the omens to be derived from what Kern translates as the ‘marks of boils’, but I think should more properly be understood as pimples.
Except on one point to which I shall refer later, his list parallels, rather than coincides with, the Thai conceptions.
In the Thai treatises a characteristic emphasis is placed on the advice that one should on no account place too much reliance on the deductions to made [sic] from pimples, but should weigh them together with any other portents that may be available.
Thus if the findings from pimples and palmistry are bad, but other portents are good, the outlook should be regarded as mixed.
Facial pimples, unlike those on the body, are more often <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.02">unfortunate than the reverse, especially for men</apodosis>.
<apodosis wn_only="good_fortune.n.01">Good ones</apodosis> are black or vermilion, <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.02">not so</apodosis> are red, white and yellow ones.
If slight, the <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.02">ill effect will be mild</apodosis>.
Those in groups of seven or five are especially favourable: if on the left they denote <apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.02, wealth.n.01, wealth.n.03">wealth</apodosis>, if on the right, <apodosis wn_only="promotion.n.02, promotion.n.03, forwarding.n.02">promotion</apodosis>.
A pimple on the left eyebrow indicates <apodosis wn_only="property.n.01">property</apodosis>, on the right <apodosis wn_only="longevity.n.02">longevity</apodosis>.
A black spot in the hair suggests <apodosis wn_only="prosperity.n.01, prosperity.n.02">prosperity</apodosis>, still more so if it is prominent.
If a group of seven are arranged on the forehead in the W-shape of the constellation Cassiopeia, this is <apodosis wn_only="good_fortune.n.01">most lucky</apodosis>.
A pimple on the ear lobe signifies <apodosis wn_only="intelligence.n.01, longevity.n.02">intelligence, long life</apodosis> if inside the ear.
Between the eyebrows indicates <apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.01, prosperity.n.02, prosperity.n.01, wealth.n.03">prosperity</apodosis>, if on the tip of the ear <apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.01, prosperity.n.02, prosperity.n.01, wealth.n.03">the prosperity will continue</apodosis>.
A pimple on the eyeball means <apodosis wn_only="gratefulness.n.01, parent.n.01, gratitude.n.01, appreciation.n.01">that person will be grateful to parents</apodosis>.
If it is situated above the middle of the upper lip it is <apodosis wn_only="luck.n.03">lucky</apodosis>, especially if black or red; otherwise only moderately so.
The following facial pimples are <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.02">unfavourable</apodosis>: at the start of the lower jaw, below the hair line, unless very small.
They mean <apodosis wn_only="trouble.n.04, trouble.n.03, trouble.n.01">trouble</apodosis>.
A pimple in the middle of the forehead means <apodosis wn_only="father.n.01, parent.n.01, mother.n.01, death.n.01">one is likely to lose father or mother</apodosis>.
If it is in the corner of an eye, just where the tears emerge, one will have <apodosis wn_only="sorrow.n.02, sorrow.n.01">continuing sorrow</apodosis>.
If it is over the cheek bone it is not at all good: <apodosis wn_only="demotion.n.01">that unlucky person, if he has rank, will be demoted</apodosis>; <apodosis wn_only="pauperization.n.02">if he has any wealth, he will lose it</apodosis>.
If it is just at the middle of the nostrils he will be <apodosis wn_only="poverty.n.01">poor</apodosis>.
If at the edge, <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.01, misfortune.n.02">not good</apodosis>, and this is also the case if the pimple is on the ear lobe or near the opening.
If it is at the tip of the nose <apodosis wn_only="ailment.n.01, foot.n.01">he is likely to have trouble with his feet</apodosis>!
And if on the sides of the nose, <apodosis wn_only="loss.n.03, property.n.01">property will be lost</apodosis>.
A pimple over the mouth means <apodosis wn_only="consequence.n.01, obloquy.n.01">that person will be likely to suffer for his remarks</apodosis>; while one near the mouth indicates <apodosis wn_only="extravagance.n.01">extravagance</apodosis>.
A pimple at the corner of the eye, or a little away, portends an <apodosis wn_only="misalliance.n.01">unfortunate marriage</apodosis>.
Pimples under the chin are <apodosis wn_only="luck.n.03, good_fortune.n.01">lucky</apodosis>.
If black ones appear all over the face, this is <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.01, misfortune.n.02">bad</apodosis> in the young, but <apodosis wn_only="luck.n.03, good_fortune.n.01">good</apodosis> in older people.
As already stated, pimples on the body are more likely to be <apodosis wn_only="luck.n.03, good_fortune.n.01">lucky</apodosis> especially in a hidden place.
They often come in pairs.
Black pimples, under the forearm and going down to the hand, are <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.02, misfortune.n.01, illness.n.01">not good, one is likely to be ill</apodosis>.
But if near the wrist, that is <apodosis wn_only="money.n.01, enrichment.n.02, good_fortune.n.01">good and money will come</apodosis>.
If right in the elbow bend—<apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.01">much money</apodosis>.
But a pimple on the elbow is <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.01">not good</apodosis>.
If one is situated on the back of the shoulder <apodosis wn_only="mastership.n.01">one will become a good craftsman</apodosis>.
If under the armpits one will become <apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.01, peace.n.03">wealthy and have consequent peace of mind</apodosis>.
A pimple near the front depression of the collar-bone is <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.01">ill-omened</apodosis>, and if on the middle of the front of the collar-bone <apodosis wn_only="larceny.n.01">thefts</apodosis> are to be expected.
A pimple on the middle of the shoulder or in front of it, signifies <apodosis wn_only="trouble.n.01">trouble</apodosis>, but on the back of it means <apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.01, enrichment.n.02, trouble.n.01">money coming</apodosis>.
A pimple on the palm or on the back of the hand portends <apodosis wn_only="prosperity.n.02">prosperity</apodosis>.
One on the front of the knee indicates the <apodosis wn_only="slaveholder.n.01">possession of many slaves</apodosis>.
At the top of the back of the leg signifies <apodosis wn_only="prosperity.n.02">prosperity</apodosis>, and so does one on or under the knee.
Pimples on the front of the leg herald <apodosis wn_only="fame.n.01">fame</apodosis>, and if on the sole of the foot <apodosis wn_only="overlord.n.01, lord.n.03">one will be a lord</apodosis>.
A pimple near the toes means <apodosis wn_only="slaveholder.n.01">many slaves</apodosis>, and on the breast <apodosis wn_only="virility.n.01, fertility.n.02">many children</apodosis>.
If under the breast one will be <apodosis wn_only="wealth.n.01">wealthy</apodosis>; if between the breasts <apodosis wn_only="happiness.n.02, longevity.n.02">will live long and be happy</apodosis> A pimple in the navel signifies <apodosis wn_only="good.n.02, child.n.02, prosperity.n.02">prosperity and good children</apodosis>, on both sides of the navel <apodosis wn_only="happiness.n.02, prosperity.n.02">prosperity and happiness</apodosis>.
If on the throat, above the Adam’s apple, one will have <apodosis wn_only="aid.n.02">constant helpers</apodosis>, but <apodosis wn_only="misfortune.n.01">not so good</apodosis> if it is below the apple, while one behind the throat indicates <apodosis wn_only="power.n.01">power</apodosis>.
A pimple over the middle of the spine portends <apodosis wn_only="longevity.n.02">long life</apodosis>.
One in the middle of the waist means <apodosis wn_only="isolation.n.01">must go and live at a distance</apodosis>, while one on the hips suggests <apodosis wn_only="rank.n.02, wealth.n.01">wealth and rank</apodosis>.
I have reserved to the last the one point on which Varāhamihira and the Thai treatises exhibit close agreement.
According to the latter a pimple on the tip of the linga portends that <apodosis wn_only="good.n.02, child.n.02">the owner will be blessed with good children</apodosis>.
For Varāhamihira, a similar appearance, in the words of Kern's translation, ‘on the membrum virile, brings <apodosis wn_only="damsel.n.01, child.n.02">a damsel and fine children</apodosis>’.
Diffusion or independent origin?
</document>
